Finding Aid for Interfaith Council for Peace and Justice (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1966-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Hunger Task Force
  - CROP Walk Topical Files
    - Church World Service Grant Applications
      - 1994-2003, 7 folders (Box 16)
    - Crop Stops
      - 1994, 2004 (Box 16)
    - Education
      - 1985-1991 (Box 16)
      - 1994-1996 (Box 16)
      - 1998-2005 (Box 16)
      - Undated (Box 16)
    - Emergency Radio Team 1989-2004 (Box 16)
    - Evaluations (Box 16)
    - Forms, Information, and Handouts 1998 (Box 16)
    - Global Economy Resources 1994-1997 (Box 16)
    - Host Congregations 2000-2002 (Box 17)
    - Hunger Coalition 1992-1995 (Box 17)
    - Hunger Meal 1994-1999 (Box 17)
    - Ideas (Box 17)
    - Junior League 1997-2003
      - 1991 (Box 17)
    - Local Hunger Groups
      - 1987-1989 (Box 17)
      - 1994-1999, 7 folders (Box 17)
      - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Logistics 1999 (Box 17)
    - Maps 1975-2007 (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Undated (Box 17)
      - 1986-1989, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - 1998-2001 (Box 17)
    - Music (Box 17)
    - Newsletter Inserts 1993 (Box 17)
    - Other Washtenaw Walks 1995-2001 (Box 17)
    - Peace Sunday 1997 (Box 17)
    - Permit 2004-2005 (Box 17)
    - Photographs Undated (Box 17)
    - Publicity
      - 1995-1999, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Recruitment
      - 1978-1984 (Box 24)
      - 1993-1999, 6 folders (Box 24)
      - 2001-2004, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Recruiter's Rally (Box 24)
    - Reference Letters (Box 24)
    - Sales: 1998-2002, 5 folders (Box 24)
    - Signs/Banners 1998-1999 (Box 24)
    - Thank You' 1991-2003 (Box 24)
    - Totals 1995-2002 (Box 24)
    - Treasury
      - 1996 (Box 24)
      - 1999 (Box 24)
    - Walk Day
      - Undated (Box 24)
      - 1999-2003 (Box 24)
    - Walker Information 1992-2003 (Box 24)
    - WIC (Women, Infants, and Children) Offering 1989 (Box 24)
    - World Food Day 1992-1996 (Box 24)
    - World Hunger Year 1994 (Box 24)
- Clergy and Laity Concerned
  The Clergy and Laity Concerned series (2.7 linear feet), documents the activities and correspondence, primarily of the organization's National Office, from 1966 to 1990. Also included are events announcements, correspondence, and newsletters from CALC Affiliate offices.
  - National Office
    - Undated
      - General (Box 18)
      - Membership, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - 1966 General (Box 18)
    - 1967
      - General (Box 18)
      - Washington, D.C. Mobilization (Box 18)
    - 1968
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Field Staff (Box 18)
      - Issues and Actions (Box 18)
      - General (Box 18)
      - Report (printed) (Box 18)
      - Steering Committee (Box 18)
    - 1969
      - Alphabetical file, 6 folders (Box 18)
      - Correspondence (Box 18)
      - Field Staff (Box 18)
      - Issues and Actions (Box 18)
      - Steering Committee (Box 18)
    - 1970
      - Field Staff (Box 18)
      - Issues and Actions (Box 18)
      - Steering Committee (Box 18)
    - 1971
      - Ann Arbor Conference, 4 folders (Box 18)
      - Correspondence (Box 18)
      - Field Staff (Box 18)
      - Financial (Box 18)
      - General (Box 18)
      - Program Office (Box 18)
      - Steering Committee (Box 18)
    - 1972
      - Correspondence (Box 19)
      - Field Staff, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Financial, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - General (Box 19)
      - Honeywell Campaign (Box 19)
      - Kansas City Conference (Box 19)
      - Manual (Box 19)
      - Reports (Box 19)
      - Report (printed) (Box 19)
      - Steering Committee, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - 1973
      - Central Region (Box 19)
      - Correspondence (Box 19)
      - Field Staff, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Financial (Box 19)
      - Lists (Box 19)
      - Michigan (primarily Ann Arbor) (Box 19)
      - Notebooks (Box 19)
      - Regional Reports (Box 19)
      - Steering Committee, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - 1974
      - Correspondence (Box 20)
      - Field Staff, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Financial, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - 1975
      - Ann Arbor (Box 20)
      - Correspondence (Box 20)
      - Field Manual (Box 20)
      - Field Staff, 4 folders (Box 20)
      - General (Box 20)
      - Steering Committee, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - 1976
      - General (Box 20)
    - 1977
      - General (Box 20)
    - 1979-May 1983
      - Correspondence (Box 20)
    - 1985
      - Changes in Bylaws (Box 20)
    - 1986
      - General (Box 20)
    - 1987
      - General (Box 20)
    - 1988
      - Correspondence (Box 20)
      - General (Box 20)
    - 1989
      - General (Box 20)
    - 1990
      - General (Box 20)
  - Affiliates
    - Atlanta (Box 20)
    - Bethlehem, PA (Box 20)
    - Boston (Box 20)
    - Chicago (Box 20)
    - Cleveland (Box 20)
    - Colorado (Box 20)
    - Detroit, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Detroit, Catholic Archdiocese of (Box 20)
    - Massachusetts (Box 20)
    - Michigan, 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Minnesota, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Mt. Clemens, MI (Box 21)
    - Nebraska (Box 21)
    - Oakland County, MI (Box 21)
    - Pacific Regional Office (Box 21)
    - Tempe, AZ (Box 21)
    - Washington, D.C. (Box 21)
- Photographs and Audiovisual Material
  The Photographs and Audiovisual Materials series (2 linear feet) includes Vietnam-era photographs, negatives, and slides of ICPJ members and events, including a Walk for Hunger and Crater Dig and a scrapbook containing photographs and fliers relating to the 2002-2003 CROP walks. Additionally there are audiotapes of a series of meeting between ICPJ members and US Representative Carl Pursell, as well as audio and video recordings of other ICPJ sponsored events and lectures.
  - Sound cassettes
    - ICPJ Events 1986-1997, 7 audiocassettes (Box 21)
    - Carl Pursell Meetings 1985-1988, 3 audiocassettes (Box 21)
  - Photographs
    - 1960s activities: include photographs and slides of demonstrations organized in opposition to America's involvement in Vietnam and to the problem of poverty and hunger in the United States; include photos of "crater digs," a March against hunger, and other protest gatherings (Box 21)
    - Walk for Hunger Scrapbook 2002-2003 (Box 21)
    - Negatives, unidentified (Box 21)
    - Slides circa 1970s Walk for Hunger (Box 21)
  - Compact Discs
    - Globalization, David Bonior and David Korton 2005 (Box 21)
    - How to File as an Conscientious Objection with David Bassett and Phil Volk (Box 21)
    - Photos of 40th Annual Meeting 2006 (Box 21)
    - Photos of E Roy Luncheon at Northside Presbyterian Church September 9, 2008 (Box 21)
  - Videotapes (VHS format)
    - Undated
      - Part I. Conduct Unbecoming; Part II. Code of Conduct (Box 22)
        (tape no. 25)
      - Debbie Billings Lecture on Guatemalan Refugees (Box 22)
        (tape no. 1)
      - Globalization (Box 22)
        (tape no.26)
      - Hikone-Ann Arbor Education Exchange Program (Box 22)
        (tape no. 2)
      - Hiroshima Day (Box 22)
        (tape no. 3)
      - Noel Paul Stookey Talks About Hunger (Box 22)
        (tape no. 4)
      - Peace Insight No. 134: Richard Fernandez, 25th Anniversary of the ICPJ (Box 22)
        (tape no. 5)
      - U. S. and Columbia: War on Drugs or War on the Poor (Box 22)
        (tape no. 6)
    - 1987
      - Dan Levitas Lecture (Box 22)
        (tape no. 7)
    - 1988
      - Art Simon of Bread for the World delivering 1988 Kauper Memorial Lecture (Box 22)
        (tape no. 27)
      - Singleton's (Box 22)
        (tape no. 8)
    - 1989
      - Ann Edgerton Alternative Defense Lecture (Box 22)
        (tape no. 9)
      - Bishop Thomas Gumbleton, "What Would We Do Without Russia as an Enemy" (Box 22)
        (tape no. 10)
      - Hiroshima Day (Box 22)
        (tape no. 11)
    - 1990
      - Anniversary, 2 tapes (Box 22)
        (tape no. 12-13)
    - 1991
      - Beverly McDonald Lecture (Box 22)
        (tape no. 14)
      - Hiroshima Day, 4 tapes (Box 22)
        (tape nos. 15-18)
    - 1996
      - ICPJ 30th Anniversary Copy#1 (Box 22)
        (tape no. 19)
      - ICPJ 30th Anniversary Copy#3 (Box 22)
        (tape no. 28)
    - 1999
      - Ariadna Bartow Human Rights in Guatemala: What's the School of the Americas Got to Do with it? (Box 22)
        (tape no. 29)
      - Stephen Zunes Lecture re: War in the Balkans (Box 22)
        (tape no. 20)
      - Betsy Barlow, Bill Thompson, Middle East Report (Box 22)
        (tape no. 32)
      - Columbia: Richard Stahler Shok (Box 22)
        (tape no. 21)
      - Kenneth Kennon: Prisoner of Conscience (Box 22)
        (tape no. 22)
    - 2003
      - Annual Meeting (Box 22)
        (tape no. 23)
      - School of the Americas Debate (Box 22)
        (tape no. 24)
    - 2004
      - Chuck, Joe, Elaine. Barriers to Peace between Israel and Palestine (Box 22)
        (tape no. 30)
      - Rachel Cocrie Event (Box 22)
        (tape no. 31)
    - 2007
      - Ruth Graves. Columbia. (Box 22)
        (tape no. 33)
  - Digital Videocassette
    - 2006
      - 15th Klein Lecture (Box 22)
        (tape no. 34)
  - Motion picture
    - "The Fading Family Farm" undated. A presentation dealing with the loss of farmland and family farmers in Washtenaw County. 15 minutes. Produced by Ken Ludwig, former country agent with Washtenaw County Extension Service slide show by Diane Wahner, a former graduate student in the UM Department of Natural Resources. (Box 22)
- Steering Committee
  The Steering Committee series (1 linear foot) is comprised of minutes, agendas, correspondence, financial, etc. documenting the decisions made during its monthly meetings. The committee nominated its members from local congregations, and met regularly to plan the activities and goals of the ICPJ.
  - 1972-2004, 34 folders (Box 25)
  - 2006-2010, 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Dates Unknown (Box 25)
- Religious Coalition on Central America/Latin American Taskforce
  The Religious Coalition on Central America (1 linear foot) series documents the working body of the ICPJ which focused on issues relating to Central American countries. The series is organized by topic as well as chronologically. Public events and encouraging dialogue within the religious community were a large part of their efforts. The RCLA was later renamed the Latin American Task Force.
  - Topical Files, bulk dates 1989-2004
    - Border Witness (Box 26)
    - Central America general (Box 26)
    - Central America Ballot Initiative (Box 26)
    - Chiapas Program (Box 26)
    - Chile (Box 26)
    - Close it Down Fast Program 2000 (Box 26)
    - Columbia (Box 26)
    - Columbus Day miscellaneous (Box 26)
    - Contra Aid (Box 26)
    - Celaya Sanctuary Family (Box 26)
    - DC Trip 1998-2002, 5 folders (Box 26)
    - Dirty Secrets Film 1998 (Box 26)
    - El Salvador (Box 26)
    - Events -- Unknown Year (Box 26)
    - Fort Benning Trip, 8 folders (Box 26)
    - Gumbleton, (Bishop) Thomas J. (Box 26)
    - Haiti (Box 26)
    - House meetings (Box 26)
    - Immigration (Box 26)
    - Jesus Tecu Osario (Box 26)
    - July 4th Parade 2003 (Box 26)
    - Managua Cathedral, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Medical Aid for El Salvador (Box 26)
    - Mexico (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 26)
    - Panama Deception Program (Box 26)
    - Press Releases (Box 26)
    - Programs 1999 (Box 26)
    - Quincentenary (1492-1992) (Box 26)
    - Repopulation of Salvadoran Countryside by Returning Refugees (Box 26)
    - The Revolution Will not be televised (event) 2004 (Box 26)
    - Archbishop Oscar Romero, Anniversary, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - School of Americas, 13 folders (Box 26)
    - Shame in Our Name Campaign 2002 (Box 26)
  - Chronological Files
    - 2000 (Box 26)
    - 2001 (Box 26)
    - 2002 (Box 26)
    - 2003 (Box 26)
    - 2004 (Box 26)
    - 2005 (Box 26)
    - 2006 (Box 26)
- Middle East Task Force
  The Middle East Task Force (1.5 linear feet) documents the working body of the ICPJ which focused on issues relating to Middle Eastern countries. The series is organized by topic as well as chronologically. Public events and encouraging dialogue within the religious community were a large part of their effort.
  - Topical Files 1997-2004
    - Action Alerts (Box 27)
    - Arms Divestment 2003 (Box 27)
    - Background (Box 27)
    - Break the Silence Campaign 1998 (Box 27)
    - Campaign to End the Israeli Occupation, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Children of Abraham (Box 27)
    - Churches for Middle East Peace 2003 (Box 27)
    - Commentary (Box 27)
    - Faber, Robert (Box 27)
    - Faith Based Statements/Perspectives
      - American Friends Service Committee Board of Directors (Box 27)
      - General (Box 27)
      - Judaism (Box 27)
    - Farah, Marya (Box 27)
    - Fundraising Committee (Box 27)
    - Fundraising Congregations 2004 (Box 27)
    - Friends of Sabeel (Box 27)
    - Gulf War Victory Parade poem 1991 (Box 27)
    - Home Demolitions 2000 (Box 27)
    - Human Rights Commission Resolution (Box 27)
    - Information Kit 2004 (Box 27)
    - Interfaith Initiative (Box 27)
    - Iraq (Box 27)
    - Islam (Box 27)
    - International Solidarity Movement (Box 27)
    - Israel/Palestine (Box 27)
    - Jewish Community Relations (Box 27)
    - Jewish Peace Lobby (Box 27)
    - Judaism (Box 27)
    - Kosovo (Box 27)
    - Mediation of METF Conflicts (Box 27)
    - Meetings 1998-2000, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Metro Detroit Against Sanctions (Box 27)
    - Middle East Mailing List (Box 27)
    - Megiddo (Box 27)
    - Middle East Delegation 1990 (Box 27)
    - Middle East Mailing List (Box 27)
    - National Organizing Conference on Iraq 1999 (Box 27)
    - New Jewish Agenda (Box 27)
    - Prayers for Peace 1998 (Box 27)
    - President Clinton/Children of Iraq Advertisement 1998 (Box 27)
    - Religious Statements
      - Episcopal (Box 27)
      - Evangelical Lutheran Church of America (Box 27)
      - Lutheran (Box 27)
      - Presbyterian (Box 27)
      - United Church of Christ (Box 27)
      - Unitarian (Box 27)
    - Secure Dwellings 1998 (Box 27)
    - Separation Wall (Box 27)
    - Stakeholder Management 2004 (Box 27)
    - Yseh Gvul (Box 27)
  - Events and Conferences
    - Corrie Family (Box 27)
    - Clark, Ramsey (Box 27)
    - Ellis, Marc (Box 27)
    - Gumbleton, (Bishop) Thomas (Box 27)
    - Halliday, Denis (Box 27)
    - Images of Iraq (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
    - Partners for Peace (Box 27)
    - Sabeel Conference (Box 27)
    - Said, Edward (Box 27)
    - Spiro, Gideon (Box 27)
  - Chronological Files
    - 1985 (Box 27)
    - 1987-1991, 5 folders (Box 27)
    - 1993 (Box 27)
    - 1994 (Box 27)
    - 1995, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - 1996 (Box 28)
    - 1998 (Box 28)
    - 2000 (Box 28)
    - 2002-2006, 5 folders (Box 28)
- Racial and Economic Task Force
  The Racial and Economic Task Force (1.5 linear feet) series documents the working body of the ICPJ which focused on promoting racial and economic justice. The series is organized by topic as well as chronologically. Public events and encouraging dialogue within the religious community were a large part of their efforts.
  - Topical Files 1993-2007
    - Anti-Michigan Civil Rights Initiative (Box 28)
    - Anti-Racist Cookbook, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Borders Concerns (Box 28)
    - Citizens Quality Healthcare 1997-1998 (Box 28)
    - Detroit Newspaper Strike (Box 28)
    - Dialogues on Diversity (Box 28)
    - Gandhi (Box 28)
    - Grant Writing (Box 28)
    - Hospital Cuts (Box 28)
    - Just Cause Law Collective (Box 28)
    - Living Wage Campaign (Box 28)
    - May 9th Rally for CommUNITY and Justice 1998 (Box 28)
    - Minimum Wage, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Non-Violent Action for Racial Justice (Box 28)
    - Ostendorf, David (Box 28)
    - Peace Team Trainings (Box 28)
    - St. Andrews Grant (Box 28)
    - Strawberry Workers (Box 28)
    - Summit on Racism (Box 28)
    - Unity Rally April 1999 (Box 28)
    - Victories without Violence (Box 28)
    - Welfare Simulation, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Willie Lynch Speech (Box 28)
    - Ypsilanti Ordinance (Box 28)
  - Chronological Files
    - 1984-1989 (Box 29)
    - 1994-2003, 10 folders (Box 29)
    - 2005-2007, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - 2009 (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous Resources and Notes (Box 29)
- Disarmament Working Group
  The Disarmament Working Group (1.5 linear feet) documents the working body of the ICPJ which focused on non-violent resolutions of personal, community, and international conflict. The series is organized by topic and as well as chronologically. Public events and encouraging dialogue within the religious community were a large part of their efforts.
  - Topical Files 1984-2004
    - Bosnia (Box 29)
    - Building permit (Box 29)
    - Caldicott, Helen (Box 29)
    - Code of Conduct (Box 29)
    - Comprehensive Test Ban (Box 29)
    - Economic Conversion (Box 29)
    - End Torture Forever! (Box 29)
    - Goldring, Natalie (Box 29)
    - Hiroshima Day (Box 29)
    - Legislation (Box 29)
    - Military Spending (Box 29)
    - MX Campaign, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 30)
    - National Council of the Churches of Christ -- USSR Travel Seminar (Box 30)
    - Non-Proliferation Treaty (Box 30)
    - Non-Proliferation Treaty -- Citizens Assembly (Box 30)
    - Nuclear Free Zone (Box 30)
    - Peace Dividend Town Meeting (Box 30)
    - Peace Fair October 1989 (Box 30)
    - Peace Sabbath 1985 (Box 30)
    - Peace Teams (Box 30)
    - Peace with Justice Week, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - Proposition One, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - Southeastern Michigan Peace and Justice Coalition (Box 30)
    - Star Wars, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Strategic Defense Initiative/Anti-Satellite Weapons (Box 30)
    - War Toys, 6 folders (Box 30)
    - World Peace Tax Fund -- War Tax Resistance (Box 30)
  - Chronological Files
    - 1994-1996, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - 2000, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - 2001 (Box 30)
    - 2003, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - 2004 (Box 30)
- Posters
  The Posters series documents the events and issues of most concern to the organization. When received this series consisted of poster board displays made up of original photographs and documents. Mainly because of their size, most of these poster board displays were photographed. Their contents were then removed from the poster boards. The folders in this series consist of a scanned photograph of each display and the individual items removed from each poster board.
  - Miscellaneous photographs and flyers taken from over-sized poster board displays, 10 folders; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 30)
    (1st folder includes CD-ROM of the posters)
  - Assorted posters for and from ICPJ events (Folder 1)
Related Material
Newsletters of the ICPJ have been removed from this record group and cataloged and located separately.